This is a 101 on Quantum Error Correcting Autoencoders.
First let's review the concepts of a classical autoencoder to understand the
motivation for turning it quantum. The autoencoder is a subclass of deep
neural networks in which the network is trained to output its input.
Autoencoders tend to have a small hidden layer, called the latent space,
which allows for a compact representation of the input. This means you
can seperate the encoder and decoder, leaving the latent space as a
compressed representation of the original content. Further, autoencoders can be used for
simultaneous denoising and compression, by training the model to return good images
even with noisy inputs.
In quantum computing, two major challenges are efficiently storing data in fewer
qubits, and error correcting. Autoencoders can solve both at once, and therefore
are a very natural architecture to adapt. I will be brief with
many explanations in the adaptation of classical to quantum autoencoder, so I
will try to leave references down on the bottom right for further
exploration. There are three key steps for training a usable autoencoder. The
forward pass. The backpropagation. And the optimizer. We already run into an
issue trying to make a quantum forward pass: Neural networks rely on
data cloning for the weights part of the forward pass. We want
to recreate the style of linear transformation that weights and biases provide,
which can be achieved using a parameterized n-qubit unitary gate. In this
example, we will focus on the computational basis, so we can reduce
the number of parameters by parameterizing with rotation gates. To decrease the
size of our latent space, we can chop off qbits. Now we
have a working forward pass, we need our backwards pass (finding the
derivative of the weights with respect to a cost function). Our cost
function will be the average fidelity between the input and output across
the training data. However, we can leverage the fact that RealAmplitudes is
unitary to half the number of nessesary parameters: we can use the
inverse of the encoder block as our decoder block. In this senario,
if the encoder block makes the bottom two qbits equal to the
|0>, then the decoder block will be able to perfectly reconstruct the
initial state. Therefore, we can greatly simplify the cost function by using
the SWAP test, which will measure a lower value if the bottom
qbits are more similar. It can also be run in hardware, rather
than simulation, since it works on measurment rather than knowing the state.
So the cost function is just getting the measurment block to measure
0 on the training data as often as possible. However, these quantum
cost functions do not provide a way for backpropigation, so we don't
know the derivative of the parameters with respect to the cost function.
Instead, we can use a derivative free optimizer, like COBYLA.
With our Quantum Autoencoder set up with a forward pass,
and optimization step, let's run it on MNIST digits! Training
goes incredibly smoothly on both Domain Wall and MNIST datasets.
So we have a simple quantum autoencoder working as well
as a simple classical autoencoder, and it actually provides significant
advantages due to the unitary encoder. So are we done?
NOOOOO, we still have error correcting quantum autoencoders!!
We need to make a couple of minor modifications to our
current training circut to support error correction. Since we intend to
change the data, we need to go back to training using
fidelity instead of the SWAP test. We also need to encode
our singular input qbit into a logical codespace, represented by |0_L⟩
= |000⟩ and |1_L⟩ = |111⟩. Finally, we include a block
that introduces errors into the training. However, as a note, if
we are training on real quantum hardware we don't need to
arifically induce errors, as the autoencoder will simply train on the
errors that occur the quantum hardware. This adaptibility makes quantum autoencoders
an incredibly powerful error correcting tool. Running with a simulated p=0.05
bit flip error on each qbit, we get the following optimizer
graph. By simply training on the |0_L⟩, |1_L⟩, and |+_L⟩ inputs,
the Quantum Autoencoder learns perfect single qbit bit flip error correction,
while still recovering the input state when no errors occur.
As a recap, we created a quantum forward pass using parameterized
rotation gates. Then we calculated a cost function using either the
SWAP test or calculating the fidelity of states. Finally, we used
COBYLA to optimize our parameters without knowing their derivative with respect
to the cost function. With this quantum autoencoder, we were able
to input qubits encoded into a logical codespace, and train the
autoencoder to remove the errors and return the original state. We
ran this all in qiskit simulation, but if this were running
on a quantum computer, it could train on the real errors
that happen in the qbits rather than our artificially incited ones.
Please see "Quantum Error Correction with Quantum Autoencoders" for more details
on the topic, but they have determined that this 3-1-3 autoencoder
error correction is always more accurate than 3 qbit actively corrected
encoding schemes when the noise inside of the error correcting network
is low (this is because the increased number of gates in
the autoencoder makes internal noise more significant).